This is part of my on-going series
on fasting for disease reversal.
I have a bunch of other
videos on fasting already,
so go to NutritionFacts.org and plug
"fasting" into the search bar for more.
"Fasting to Reverse Diabetes"
Currently nearly half a billion
adults have diabetes,
and a 50% increase is
expected in another generation.
I've got tons of videos on
the best diets for diabetes,
but what about no diet at all?
More than a century ago,
fasting was said to bring
about the cure of diabetes,
speedily arresting its development
and causing complete disappearance
of all its manifestations
in several days or weeks.
Even so, starvation is
guaranteed to lead to
the complete disappearance
of you, if kept up long enough.
What's the point of fasting it away,
if it's just going to come raging back
as soon as you restart the diet
that caused it in the first place?
Might it be useful to kind of
kickstart a healthier diet?
Let's see what the science says.
Type 2 diabetes has long been
recognized as a disease of excess,
a disease of the idle rich,
by which they mean anyone
who doesn't practice
sustained vigorous
bodily exertion every day,
and earning enough to regularly
eat more than they need.
So diabetes is preventable,
but then maybe it's also treatable.
If we are dying of overeating, maybe
we can be saved by undereating.
Remarkably this was suggested about
2,000 years ago in an Ayurvedic text.
Diabetics were encouraged
to live like a saint, walk for, oh,
800 or 900 miles, dig a pond, or live
only on cow dung and cow urine.
That reminds me of the Rollo diet
for diabetes proposed in 1797,
composed of a diet of rancid meat.
That was on top of the ipecac-like drugs
he used to produce
severe sickness and vomiting.
Anything that produces sickness has
a temporary effect in relieving diabetes
by diminishing the
quantity of food eaten.
And his diet plan —
congealed blood for lunch
and spoiled meat for dinner —
certainly had that effect.
Similar benefits were seen in
diabetics during the siege of Paris
in the Franco-Prussian War,
leading to the advice to
'mangez le moins possible'
(eat as little as possible).
That was formalized into
the Allen Starvation treatment,
considered to be the greatest medical
advance in the treatment of diabetes
prior to the discovery of insulin.
Before insulin, there was the Allen Era.
He noted reports in the clinical literature
of even severe diabetics clearing up
on wasting diseases like tuberculosis,
so he decided to put it to the test.
He found that even the
most severe type of diabetes,
he could clear sugar from
people's urine within 10 days.
Of course, that's the easy part.
It's maintaining it
once you start eating again,
for which he stuck to two principles:
keeping them underweight
and restricting the quantity of fat.
A severe diabetic can be
symptom-free for days or weeks,
but add some butter or olive oil and
the disease can come raging back.
As I covered before, diabetes
is a disease of fat toxicity.
Infuse fat into people's
veins through an IV,
and by using a high-tech
type of MRI scanner,
you can show in real time the buildup
of fat in muscle cells within hours,
accompanied by an increase
in insulin resistance.
The same thing happens when you put
people on a high-fat diet for three days,
or even just one day,
or even just a single meal can increase
insulin resistance within six hours.
Acute dietary fat intake rapidly
increases insulin resistance.
Why do we care?
Because insulin resistance
in our muscles, in the context
of too many calories, leads to
the buildup of liver fat, which leads
to the buildup of fat in the pancreas,
which is eventually what
causes diabetes.
Type 2 diabetes can now
be understood as a state
of excess fat in the
liver and pancreas
and remains reversible for at least
10 years in most individuals.
Put people on a very low-calorie
diet, 700 calories a day,
and fat can get sucked
out of your muscle cells,
and you get a corresponding
boost in insulin sensitivity.
Fat is then sucked out of your liver,
and if you keep it up the fat gets
sucked out of your pancreas.
And if you catch it early enough
that can mean a reversal
of your type 2 diabetes, meaning
normal sugars on a normal diet.
With the loss of 15% of body weight,
nearly 90% of those who've had
type 2 diabetes for less than four
years can achieve remission,
where it may only be reversible in 50%
of those who've lived with the disease
for longer than eight years.
That's better than bariatric surgery,
where those losing even more weight
only got 62 and 26% remissions.
Your forks are better
than the surgeon's knives.
Here's how much weight you have to
lose to achieve various remission rates
for those who've had diabetes
for an average of three years.
Lose about 30 pounds and most
newly diagnosed type 2 diabetics
can reverse their disease. So an
extended bout of physician-supervised,
water-only fasting could get you there,
but you have to maintain
the weight loss.
One of the things we
can say with certainty
is that if you regain the weight,
you regain your diabetes.
To bring it full circle,
the initial euphoria about
medicine's greatest miracle,
the discovery of insulin in 1921,
soon gave way to the realization
that while it was literally a life-saver
for type 1 diabetics, the use of insulin
on its own in type 2 diabetics
would not be enough to prevent
the later onset of complications
like kidney failure, blindness,
stroke, amputations.
So, as argued by one the most famous
diabetes pioneers, Elliot Joslin,
self-discipline on diet and exercise,
as it was in the days prior to insulin,
should be central to the
management of diabetes.